Miguel Rivera-Lanas

Data scientist with 3 years of experience in the asset management industry, looking to pivot into a data engineer or data scientist role. Hoping to work with a team of data scientists and engineers focused on products and solutions emphasizing differentiated approaches to employing big data and machine learning.

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist — **Point72**, New York City, NY **September 2019 - Present**

- Research applications and best practices for data science and engineering.
 Apply large scale/alternative data using ETL processes and statistical methods to improve the equity investment process.
- Use **Pyspark** to analyze unstructured columnar data, like credit-card transactions and website clickstream datasets. Use **SpaCy** for document pre-processing and information extraction from streaming text data.
- Use **Airflow**, **Jinja** and **AWS S3/SQS/Lambda** to build and maintain data pipelines, and **Dash** to create web based dashboards for end users.

Research Associate — AllianceBernstein, New York City, NY June 2016 - August 2016 (Summer Internship), June 2017 - August 2019

- Monthly projects focused on tracking fiscal deficits, debt balances, and trade balances for emerging market countries issuing sovereign debt. Automated ingestion and high level analysis using R Markdown.
- Maintained output and delivered monthly updates from GAM model (**R**, **mgcv**) used for explaining bond price dispersion.
- Developed and maintained ETL using MySQL for extracting liquidity signals from live order-book data and developed Jupyter Notebook dashboards utilized by traders.
- Wrote a pipeline using **MySQL** and **BeautifulSoup** to web-scrape and analyze online resources for GHG emissions data from municipal utilities for an environmental scorecard used by ESG impact analysis.

Research Assistant — Wharton Management Dep., Philadelphia, PA September 2015 - May 2016

 Researched upstream transnational energy infrastructure projects as part of a long term study focusing on project management best-practices. Focused on effects of macroeconomic events and operational decisions.

EDUCATION

University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA — *B.A., Cum Laude* **August 2013 - May 2017**

Major: Economics, Minors(s): Statistics, International Relations

Extracurriculars:

- Check One: Board Member. Student organization providing a space for discussions about personal and societal experiences about race and mixed-heritage backgrounds.
- **Penn Journal of Economics:** *Editorial Committee.* (PJE) is a semi-annual, peer-reviewed publication of honors theses and other academic projects for undergraduates and faculty.

Email:

miguelriveralanas@gmail.com

Github: rivera-lanasm **Website:** rivera-lanasm.com

CORE COMPETENCIES

Scripting Languages: Python, R,

Scala, SOL

Development Tools: Git, Airflow,

Bash, Jinja

Big Data: Spark (Scala/PySpark), DBT, AWS (EC2, Lambda, S3,

Athena, SQS)

Databases: MySQL, PostgresSQL,

MongoDB, Redis, Hive

ML: Sklearn, SpaCy, Tensorflow Visualization/Web: Dash, Flask,

BeautifulSoup

INTERESTS

Philosophy, Political Documentaries, Programming, Probability/Statistics, Distributed Computing, and Machine Learning

PERSONAL PROJECTS

(rivera-lanasm.com):

- Kaggle, NLP: Quora Sincere Ouestion Classification
- Tested transfer learning and word embedding techniques, and various model architectures and tuning methods in **TensorFlow** to detect "insincere" questions on Quora.
- 538 Riddler Solutions:
- -Logic and math puzzles solved with analytical and simulation/probabilistic methods. Solutions coded primarily in **Scala**.

LANGUAGES

English (Fluent)
Spanish (Fluent)

 Language accreditation from Escuela Argentina of Washington D.C.

French (Working Proficiency)

 2012 VA Governor's School-French Language Immersion Program